A Guide to the Marjorie and Robert Lundegard Papers, 1971-2018
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Marjorie and Robert Lundegard Papers, 1971-2018
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 06-107
6.0 linear feet
The Marjorie and Robert Lundegard Papers consists of 6.0 linear feet and spans the years 1971-2018. It consists of articles, newspaper clippings, photographs, photocopies, postcards, maps, travel pamphlets, newsletters, correspondence, journal entries, and notes concerning their research on grist mills.
Marjorie Lundegard (1920-2022) and Robert J. Lundegard (1927-2019)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Donated by Marjorie Lundegard through her son, Paul Lundegard in November 2019.
Historical and Biographical Information
Robert James Lundegard was born on February 22, 1927, in Youngstown, Ohio. During World War II, he joined the Navy while still in high school. Bob used the G.I. Bill to graduate from Purdue University with an M.S. in Statistics in 1952, and a Ph.D. in Statistics in 1956. While at Purdue, he met Mary Marjorie Jones, who was born on August 10, 1920, in Bourbon, Indiana. She had earned her bachelor's and master's degrees in Chemistry and Physics from Purdue. The couple were married by the Justice of the Peace in his office in Lafayette, Indiana on September 7, 1951.
The Lundegards initially moved to Syracuse, NY where Bob taught at Syracuse University, and Marge became a high school math teacher. In September 1961, the Lundegards relocated to Fairfax County and purchased a house in the Courtland Park neighborhood in Falls Church. Bob went on to have a distinguished career at the Office of Naval Research and became its Deputy Director. In 1987, he was appointed Chief of Statistical Engineering at the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST). He retired in 1991. Marge taught science at Flint Hill School and later Oakton High School. The Washington Science Teachers Association and Fairfax County Public Schools both recognized her as an Outstanding Teacher of Chemistry.
After retiring from Oakton High School in 1988, Marge began volunteering at Sully Historic Site in Chantilly. Because the commute to Sully became increasingly difficult, she switched to volunteering closer to home at Colvin Run Mill in Great Falls. This led to an avid interest in mills and milling. She and Bob started stopping at old mills on their travels which they began chronicling in a column in the Colvin Run Mill Newsletter called "On the Road with Marge and Bob."
During their retirement, both Bob and Marge spent over 25,000 hours volunteering at Colvin Run Mill and passionately pushed for its restoration. They were founding members of the Friends of Colvin Run Mill in 1997, and Bob went on to be the organization’s president. Marge researched and documented mills around Northern Virginia, and she wrote over 22 publications on mills and mill sites in Virginia, Maryland, Washington, D.C., Delaware and Pennsylvania. All proceeds from her publications went towards the mill, and together, Marge and Bob raised more than $50,000 to support Colvin Run Mill’s capital improvements plan. Marge’s research and documentation on mills earned her the Great Falls Historical Society’s Jean Tibbetts History Award in May 2012.
In addition to his involvement with Colvin Run Mill, Bob Lundegard also spent his retirement as President and Circulation Manager of the Society for the Preservation of Old Mills Mid-Atlantic Chapter, and served on the Board of the Great Falls Senior Center and Great Falls Historical Society. The couple also spent time volunteering at Inova Fairfax Hospital's Treasure Trove store in McLean.
Bob Lundegard passed away on May 20, 2019. That July, the Fairfax County Park Authority voted to rename the barn at Colvin Run Mill, the “Marjorie and Robert J. Lundegard Education Center”. Marge Lundegard passed away on May 10, 2022, at age 101.
Scope and Content
The Marjorie and Robert Lundegard Papers consists of 6.0 linear feet and spans the years 1971-2018. It consists of articles, newspaper clippings, photographs, photocopies, postcards, maps, travel pamphlets, newsletters, correspondence, journal entries, and notes concerning their research on grist mills. The bulk of their research was focused on mills and mill sites in Virginia, but they also researched sites throughout the United States and internationally.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
None.
Index Terms
Colvin Run Mill.; Great Falls (Va.) -- History.; Historic sites -- Virginia -- Great Falls.; Lundegard, Marjorie (1920-2022); Lundegard, Robert J. (1927-2019); Mills and mill-work -- Virginia; Mills and mill-work -- Virginia -- Fairfax County.
Container List
- Background Data on the Flour Inspection System in Virginia (1760-1860) (1 of 3), 2009-2011
- Background Data on the Flour Inspection System in Virginia (1760-1860) (2 of 3), 2009-2011
- Background Data on the Flour Inspection System in Virginia (1760-1860) (3 of 3), 2009-2011
- Barrels, Undated
- Canals, 1998
- Colvin Run Historic District, 2006-2007
- Colvin Run School, Undated
- Covered Bridges, 2005-2008
- Dranesville Tavern, Undated
- History of Early American Flour Milling (1 of 2), 2006
- History of Early American Flour Milling (2 of 2), 2006
- Karen Washburn Articles (1 of 2), 2005-2007
- Karen Washburn Articles (2 of 2), 2009-2011
- Mill Carpentry, Undated
- Mill Photos in Mayo Stuntz Photo Collection, Undated
- Mill Science, 2004-2017
- Milling Industry, Undated
- Mills - Alabama, Undated
- Mills - Arkansas, Undated
- Mills - California, 1981-1998
- Mills - Canada, 1997-2001
- Mills - Colorado, Undated
- Mills - Connecticut, Undated
- Mills - Delaware - Kent, New Castle, and Sussex Counties, 1994-2006
- Mills - Georgia, 1997-1998
- Mills - Illinois, 1972-2002
- Mills - Indiana (1 of 2), 2000-2010
- Mills - Indiana (2 of 2), 1995-2007
- Mills - Iowa, Undated
- Mills - Ireland, Undated
- Mills - Kansas, Undated
- Mills - Kentucky, Undated
- Mills - Maryland, 2002-2012
- Mills - Maryland - Allegany County - Folck's Mill, 2009
- Mills - Maryland - Allegany County - Lonaconing Silk Mill, 2002-2004
- Mills - Maryland - Baltimore County, 2005
- Mills - Maryland - Caroline County, Undated
- Mills - Maryland - Caroline County - Linchester Mill, 1974-2005
- Mills - Maryland - Caroll County, Undated
- Mills - Maryland - Caroll County - McKinstry Mill, Undated
- Mills - Maryland - Charles County, Undated
- Mills - Maryland - Charles County - Millbrook Mill, 2009
- Mills - Maryland - Frederick County, 1998
- Mills - Maryland - Garrett County, Undated
- Mills - Maryland - Harford County, Undated
- Mills - Maryland - Howard County, 2003
- Mills - Maryland - Montgomery County, 2002
- Mills - Maryland - Prince George's County, Undated
- Mills - Maryland - St. Mary's County, Undated
- Mills - Maryland - Talbot County - Wye Mill, Undated
- Mills - Maryland - Washington County, 1999
- Mills - Maryland - Wicomico County - Double Mills, Undated
- Mills - Massachusetts, Undated
- Mills - Michigan, Undated
- Mills - Michigan - St. Joseph County - Flowerfield Mill, 2010
- Mills - Missouri, 1992-2012
- Mills - New Jersey, 1986-2008
- Mills - New Mexico, Undated
- Mills - New York, 1996-2007
- Mills - New York - Delaware County - Hanford Mills Museum, Undated
- Mills - New York - Rochester, Undated
- Mills - New York - St. Lawrence County - Morrison Mills, 2008-2011
- Mills - North Carolina, 2002-2010
- Mills - Ohio, 1988-2008
- Mills - Oregon, Undated
- Mills - Pennsylvania (1 of 2), Undated
- Mills - Pennsylvania (2 of 2), 1976-2004
- Mills - Pennsylvania - Adams County, 1991-2001
- Mills - Pennsylvania - Fitz Waterwheel Company, 1998
- Mills - Pennsylvania - Lehigh County - Betz Mill, 1987
- Mills - Pennsylvania - York County, 1996-2011
- Mills - Rhode Island, Undated
- Mills - South Carolina, 2002
- Mills - South Carolina - Pickens County, 1997-2002
- Mills - Switzerland/Black Forest, 2005
- Mills - Tennessee, 1984-2004
- Mills - Tennessee - Franklin County - Falls Mill, 1985-2007
- Mills - Texas, Undated
- Mills - Unidentified, 1976-2007
- Mills - Utah, 1998-2006
- Mills - Vermont, 2006
- Mills - Virginia, 2000-2006
- Mills - Virginia - Accomack County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Albemarle County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Alexandria and Arlington Counties, 2005-2008
- Mills - Virginia - Amelia County, 1995
- Mills - Virginia - Amherst County, 1987-2000
- Mills - Virginia - Appomattox County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Augusta County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Bath County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Bedford County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Buckingham County, 1995
- Mills - Virginia - Campbell County, 1971-1981
- Mills - Virginia - Caroline County, 1999
- Mills - Virginia - Carroll County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Chesterfield County, 1995
- Mills - Virginia - Clarke County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Craig County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Culpeper County, 2005
- Mills - Virginia - Cumberland County, 1995-2005
- Mills - Virginia - Essex County, 1998
- Mills - Virginia - Fairfax County, 1993-2004
- Mills - Virginia - Fairfax County - Barcroft Mill, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Fairfax County - Cabell's Mill, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Fairfax County - Colvin Run Mill, 1993-2007
- Mills - Virginia - Fairfax County - Colvin Run Mill - Clifford Currie (1 of 3), 2003
- Mills - Virginia - Fairfax County - Colvin Run Mill - Clifford Currie (2 of 3), 2002
- Mills - Virginia - Fairfax County - Colvin Run Mill - Clifford Currie (3 of 3), Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Fairfax County - Colvin Run Mill - Friends of Colvin Run Mill, 2012-2016
- Mills - Virginia - Fairfax County - Colvin Run Mill - Friends of Colvin Run Mill - Mill Visit Passport, 2002-2004
- Mills - Virginia - Fairfax County - Four Mile Run, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Fairfax County - George Washington's Gristmill, 1971-2002
- Mills - Virginia - Fairfax County - Holmes Run/Difficult Run, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Fairfax County - Hunter's Mill, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Fauquier County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Floyd County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Fluvanna County, 2018
- Mills - Virginia - Franklin County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Frederick County, 1994
- Mills - Virginia - Fredericksburg, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Gloucester County, 2005
- Mills - Virginia - Goochland County, 1997
- Mills - Virginia - Greene County, 2003-2004
- Mills - Virginia - Hanover County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Henrico County, 2004
- Mills - Virginia - Highland County, 2005
- Mills - Virginia - King and Queen County, 1994
- Mills - Virginia - King William County, 2009
- Mills - Virginia - Lancaster County, 1998-2005
- Mills - Virginia - Lee County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Loudoun County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Loudoun County - Aldie Mill, 1984-1995
- Mills - Virginia - Lunenburg County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Lynchburg, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Madison County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Matthews County, 2007-2010
- Mills - Virginia - Matthews County - Poplar Grove Tide Mill, 1994
- Mills - Virginia - Middlesex County, 1998
- Mills - Virginia - Nelson County, 1998
- Mills - Virginia - Nelson County - Midway Mill, 2003
- Mills - Virginia - New Kent County, 1997-2009
- Mills - Virginia - Northumberland County, 1998-2000
- Mills - Virginia - Orange County, 2005
- Mills - Virginia - Page County, 2004
- Mills - Virginia - Patrick County, 1999
- Mills - Virginia - Pittsylvania County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Powhatan County, 1997
- Mills - Virginia - Prince George County, 1997
- Mills - Virginia - Prince William County
- Mills - Virginia - Prince William County - Beverley Chapman Mill, 1998-2002
- Mills - Virginia - Rappahannock County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Richmond County, 2001
- Mills - Virginia - Rockbridge County, 1984-1997
- Mills - Virginia - Rockingham County, 1996
- Mills - Virginia - Scott County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Shenandoah County, 2005
- Mills - Virginia - Smyth County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Stafford County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Tazewell County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Warren County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Washington County, 1999-2002
- Mills - Virginia - Westmoreland County - Purcell Mills, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - Westmoreland County - Stratford Hall Grist Mill, 1996
- Mills - Virginia - Wythe County, Undated
- Mills - Virginia - York County, 1997-2004
- Mills - Washington, Undated
- Mills - Washington, D.C., 2005
- Mills - Washington, D.C. - Pierce Mill, 1987-2008
- Mills - West Virginia, 1999-2005
- Mills - Wisconsin - Rock County - Beckman Mill, 2000-2018
- Mills on the National Register, Undated
- Mutual Assurance Society Records, 2007
- Oliver Evans, Undated
- The International Molinological Society (TIMS), 2000
- Windmills, 2007